Guide to the Brooklyn Bridge construction records 1977.259
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Bridge construction records
circa 1860s-1870s
1877-1879
Brooklyn Historical Society
Roebling, Washington Augustus
Dunn, John
New York Bridge Company
1977.259
0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box.
This collection consists of notes, letters, engineering computations, reports, specifications, inventories, and clippings relating to the construction of the Brooklyn Bridge. The correspondence includes notes to Washington Roebling, as well as some items in his hand.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Dunn, 1966. Dunn collected these materials from the trash during the demolition of a city-owned building where he was a workman.
Historical note
The Brooklyn Bridge is a steel suspension bridge that spans the East River connecting the boroughs of Manhattan and Brooklyn in New York City. Completed in 1883, the bridge was called both the East River Bridge and the New York and Brooklyn Bridge until 1915 when the name was officially changed to the Brooklyn Bridge. The bridge was designated a National Historic Landmark in 1964 and was further designated a National Historic Civil Engineering Landmark in 1972. The original designer of the bridge was John Augustus Roebling (1806-1869), a German engineer who immigrated to the United States in 1831. Roebling invented the wire cable which he would eventually incorporate into the design of the Brooklyn Bridge. Roebling's son, Washington Augustus Roebling (1837-1926), also an engineer, took over as chief engineer of construction following the sudden death of his father in 1869. In 1872, Washington Roebling fell ill with decompression sickness, acquired during the construction of the bridge, and never fully recovered. His wife, Emily Warren Roebling (1843-1903), was instrumental in seeing through the construction and completion of the bridge.
Sources:
Fletcher, Ellen. "John Augustus Roebling." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson, 1017. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Fletcher, Ellen. "Washington Augustus Roebling." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, edited by Kenneth T. Jackson, 1017. New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Related Materials
Washington A. Roebling family letters (1992.020)
Washington A. Roebling notes to Harvey Cooley (1977.238)
John Cazzetto photograph collection on the John A. Roebling II family (V1992.016)
New York & Brooklyn Bridge and Brooklyn City viewbook (V1986.005)
Brooklyn periodical illustrations (BCMS.0003), Folder: Bridges: Brooklyn Bridge
E.E. Rutter photographs (BCMS.0004), Photographs by subject: Brooklyn Bridge
The New-York Historical Society holds the William H. Paine Papers (MS 475)
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of notes, letters, engineering computations, reports, specifications, inventories, and clippings relating to the construction of the Brooklyn Bridge. The correspondence includes notes to Washington Roebling, as well as some items in his hand. The clippings and notes include information about other engineering projects, including in Virginia, as well as general scientific information related to the bridge's construction.
Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Bridges -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- Design and construction; Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Civil engineering -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Reports; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Calculations; Architectural records; Inventories; Specifications; Civil engineering -- United States; Engineering; Engineering and construction; Roebling, Washington Augustus; Dunn, John; New York Bridge Company; New York (N.Y.). Board of Trustees of the New York and Brooklyn Bridge; Martin, Charles Cyril, 1831-1903; Paine, William H.
- Series 1: Documents
  - Sub-series 1.1: Washington A. Roebling correspondence and papers (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Roebling, Washington A., notes re Brooklyn anchorage, 1873
    - Sellers, George H. to Col. W.A. Roebling, 1878
    - Sellers, George H., Wilmington, DE to Col. W. A. Roebling, 1878
    - Roebling, W.A. per EWH to Col. Paine, 1878
  - Sub-series 1.2: William H. Paine correspondence and papers (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Biographical note
    Originally from New Hampshire, Colonel William Paine was an experienced surveyor hired to work on the Brooklyn Bridge in 1869. He was self-taught in engineering, and had previously surveyed the Johnson Route of the Union Pacific railroad. During the Civil War, President Lincoln had named him a captain of engineers on the staff of a major general after he snuck into Confederate territory and mapped every destroyed bridge between Washington and Richmond. By the war's end, he was supposedly known as one of the Union Army's best topographical engineers.
    Source:
    McCullough, David. The Great Bridge. New York, NY: Simon and Schuster, 1972. p. 86.
    - Murphy, Henry C. to Col., 1879
    - Macdonald, Charles to Col. Paine, 1878
    - Linville, J.H. to Col. Paine, 1878
      Scope and Contents
      Telegram via Western Union from Linville, J. H., Philadelphia to Col. W.H. Paine.
    - Sellers, George H., Wilmington, D.E. to Col. Paine, 1878
    - Mulqueen, John H. Note re inventory of coils to Col. Paine, 1878
    - Linville, J.H., Philadelphia, PA to W.H. Paine, 1878
    - Notes, lists, letters re wire tests to Col. W.H. Paine from Robb Mackie, C.H. Platt, 1878
  - Sub-series 1.3: Pipe coupling suit correspondence and documents (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters and notes from Chas. F. Blake, N. Y., to Wm. H. Paine, 1878-1879
    - Allison, W.C.: letters, sketches and notes re claim re pipe coupling, 1877-1879
    - Abbott, A.V. to Col. Paine, circa 1870s
  - Sub-series 1.4: Charles Cyril Martin correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Charles Cyril (C.C.) Martin was an assistant engineer on the Roeblings' engineering staff, second only to the Roeblings themselves. He was a graduate of Rensselaer and had worked on three reservoir projects with William Kingsley, as well as having laid one of Brooklyn's water mains and serving as head engineer in the building of Prospect Park. Martin was named Chief Engineer on July 9, 1883 after Washington Roebling submitted his resignation, and held the title until 1902.
    McCullough, David. The Great Bridge. New York, NY: Simon and Schuster. pp. 146, 545.
    - Telegram via Western Union from Roeblings Sons Co., Trenton, N.J. to Col. C.C. Martin, 1878
    - Martin, Col. C.C., Brooklyn to Col. Paine, 1878
    - Abbott, Arthur V., Brooklyn to Martin, C.C., 1878
  - Sub-series 1.5: Specifications for work and materials (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Report on comparative processes for making iron eye bars, 1873-1874
    - Edge Moor Iron Co. reports of tests of iron, 1878
    - Mayor Cooper notes for suggested revision of specifications, 1879
    - Specifications and statements re quality of materials, circa 1879
    - Specifications for the iron work, 1878
    - Specifications for the steel and iron work with amendments by Mayor Cooper, 1879
    - Specifications for steel and iron work office work sheets, 1878-1879
    - Specifications for Steel Cable Wire and note, 1876, 1878
      5 copies of printed specifications, 1876. Also includes handwritten note from Robb Mackie to Col. Paine, 1878.
    - List of names and addresses to which copies of specifications were sent, 1876
  - Sub-series 1.6: Reports, notes, and administrative documents (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - King Iron Bridge Co. diagram of strains for iron truss bridge, circa 1870s
    - Wire test analysis sheet, 1877
    - Paine, W.H. to Martin, C.C. re wire testing, circa 1870s
    - Estimate of "cheapest viaduct" building costs, 1878
    - Test reports with some specifications for cable and wire, circa 1870s
    - Fords, Ferry and Bridges of the Potomac, circa 1860s-1870s
    - Fords, Roads and Mileages of Virginia notebook, circa 1863
    - Chronology of proceedings re contracts for superstructure, 1878-1880
    - Contract forms, 1878
    - Wire record signed by Farrington, F.D., 1878
    - Inventory of wire signed by F.D. Farrington, 1878
  - Sub-series 1.7: Clippings and ephemera, circa 1870s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Clippings from technical magazines and newspapers re construction and engineering problems; business card of William H. Wallace & Co., Iron Merchants, N.Y.; U.S. Centennial Exposition pamphlets describing exhibits there of the American Bridge Co. and Keystone Bridge Co.; blueprint marked "Suspension."
- Series 2: Publications
  - New York Bridge Company, Reports of the Executive Committee and Treasurer of the New York Bridge Co. Brooklyn, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Trustees of the New York and Brooklyn Bridge, Communication to The Board of Aldermen of the City of New York by the President of the Trustees, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Prentice, John H. Report of the Treasurer of the New York and Brooklyn Bridge, 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Engineers Day books recording tests conducted, 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    Two leatherbound volumes numbered 6 and 66. A third numbered 46 is missing as of 2024.